<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The falling stars or the dragons bringing down, and trampling upon heavenly glory. By John Eston, sometime fellow of Oriel Coll. Oxon.</title>
            <author>Eston, John, 1625 or 6-1689.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84127</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3356</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1361_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209202</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868094</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868094</idno>
            <idno type="VID">169844</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84127)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169844)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 179:E1361[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The falling stars or the dragons bringing down, and trampling upon heavenly glory. By John Eston, sometime fellow of Oriel Coll. Oxon.</title>
                  <author>Eston, John, 1625 or 6-1689.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[62], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Francis Leach,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "ffeb: 9th 1652"; 3 in imprint date crossed through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelation XII --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Dragons --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Clergy --  Office --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:169844:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE FALLING STARS, OR THE DRAGONS Bringing down, and trampling upon, HEA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VENLY GLORY.</p>
            <p>BY JOHN ESTON, ſometime Fellow of <hi>Oriel</hi> Coll. <hi>Oxon.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Joh. 2.19.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>They went out from us, but they were not of us: for if they had been of us, they would no doubt have continued with us; but they went out that they might be made manifeſt, that they were not all of us.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Francis Leach,</hi> 1653.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:169844:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:169844:2"/>
            <head>To all that love the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, in <hi>Martines Vintry.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THis little Peece was never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for publick view, only to diſcharge my duty at the late erected Exerciſe at <hi>Thomas Apoſtles,</hi> where I not long ſince, by the providence of God, in the deſires of my fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low laborers in the Vineyard, was called to work. I did not in my preparatory medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions conſult with fleſh and blood, what might gain me eſteem with that Audito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; what doctrine might probably be moſt taking, and ſuit beſt with the diſpoſitions of the people: but laying aſide all by-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, which to the praiſe of grace be it spoken, I was reſolved to deliver what my own ſpirit was convinced of for a truth, and was moſt agreeable to this tottering and declining age. It pleaſed God to fix my unſetled thoughts amongſt the varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb facs="tcp:169844:3"/>of Texts, upon that place of Scripture <hi>Rev. 1 2.4.</hi> I was not diſobedient to this heavenly ſuggeſtion, however I was not then ignorant, how ſome, whoſe tempers I very well underſtand, would diſgust and diſrelliſh that matter, the words of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to be ſpoken to; yet this I can ſay, but one I ever heard of was diſſatisfied in, and diſſented from, what was laid down, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as contrary to the Analogy of Faith, or the true ſenſe and meaning of Chriſt in the Viſion I ſhall leave it to the ſpirituall man, who judgeth all things, to examine this little Treatiſe; I refuſe to put my ſelf upon the tryal of thoſe, who whileſt they boult out their own opinions with ſuch confidence, as Authentic all, they are guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of that which themſelves cry down, a Papall infallibility. To wave what I could ſay for my ſelf, concerning the releaſing of this poor Priſoner at the Barre, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him liberty to wander at large, (though I know the modeſty of ſome, with the diſſimulations and flatteries of others, have brought Apologies into faſhion,) I ſhall addreſs my ſelf to you, with whom, according to the weak gifts in me, I have for a Twelve moneth laid open the unſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chable riches of Chriſt, and I muſt needs
<pb facs="tcp:169844:3"/>ſay, both my Perſon and Miniſtry hath been entertained with the love and reſpect of divers, more than could be expected by one comming in upon ſuch diſadvantage as my ſelf; it will adde much to my engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, if you will but give ſhelter to this poor Pilgrim of mine, now upon travell; I cannot tell, but that by reaſon of ſtorms it may be neceſſitated to houſe ſomewhere, I beſeech you think never the worſe of it, becauſe it viſits you in a homely dreſſe, like that plain mind from whence it went out, voyd of all ornaments and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodations which may ſet it out and commend it. My confidence is, however ſome in theſe curious times may cenſure and judge of me, yet you will accept of my Endeavours, as a ſtanding pledge and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of that love and ſervice I now doe, and hope ever ſhall bear unto you in the Goſpel. Out of inward bowels, I pray that may never happen to you, which did to theſe Starres (being indeed nothing but tranſitory impreſſions in the Air) For this Cauſe I bow my knees to the Father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, that your light may alwaies ſhine before men, that no wiles of the Dragon may ſo far prevail as to caſt you down from your
<pb facs="tcp:169844:4"/>good beginnings. I know not what better to wiſh you (which is my hearts deſire) that you may be ſaved; and becauſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe is the way to happineſſe, I pray God keep you pure and unſpotted, that ſo when Chriſt, who is your life, ſhall appear, you may then appear with him in Glory. Now to him who is able to ſtrengthen and eſtabliſh you, I commend you, and reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours, in the common Saviour,</hi> John Eſton.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:169844:4"/>
            <head>THE FALLING STARS.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>REVEL. 12. the former part of the 4th verſe.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And his tayl drew down the third part of the ſtars of heaven, and did cast them to the earth.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His book was the laſt breath, wherewith the Penmen of holy Writ were inſpired, and the laſt love-token of a kind Husband to his Spouſe; Chriſt handed it to us by <hi>John</hi> the beloved Diſciple, he was a ſpeciall favorite, one that did lean upon Chriſts breaſt; therefore he above the reſt was
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:169844:5"/>honoured with ſpeciall ſecrets, and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom counſells; He was made one of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens Privy-counſell, having the futuriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of things preſented to him; The mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter here treated of is altogether prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall, <hi>(viz.)</hi> concerning the Church, her perſecutions by enemies. The mutations of the viſible ſtate thereof, defections of Apoſtates, &amp; fearful cloudings and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of the light of the Goſpel: In brief, we have here a generall view and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of all the conditions of Gods people, untill the ſecond comming of Chriſt. Some have thought this Chapter to be the whole <hi>Apocalyps</hi> in a leſſer volume. In it we have the preparations and skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhes between the old Serpent and <hi>Michael,</hi> the two Generalls of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and the mutuall ſucceſſe of both Parties; this was brought to <hi>John</hi> in two Viſions, both which he gives an exact ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt of; the firſt viſion he deſcribes, 1. From the quantity, it was a great wonder, 2. From the place, in heaven, 3. From the form, a Woman, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> the Church militant, becauſe ſhe is cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and put to flight, which cannot be ſaid of the eſtate triumphant, then the Saints are at reſt; She is called a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:169844:5"/>becauſe of ſelf-impotency and inſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency, not being able to doe any thing without Chriſt, no more than the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man without her husband. This woman hath three Externall adjuncts, 1. Cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with the Sunne, that is Chriſt, ſo called in Scripture, <hi>Mal.</hi> 4.2. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the Moon under her feet, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that is, in her Affections, which are the feet to carry the ſoul, ſhe tramples upon ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene things as inconſtant as the Moon. Thirdly, a ſtarry crown; and three In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, ver. 2. She was with child ſhe travelled in birth, and in pain to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered; not of Chriſt, as ſome think, for he is not the ſeed, but the father of the Church; but of ſome Magiſtrate or Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, who was to be inſtrumental for her preſervation and deliverance. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Viſion is deſcribed, 1. From the place, in heaven, 2. From the quantity, great, 3. From the form, a Dragon, 4. From the colour, red, 5. From his monſtrous ſhape and figure, having ſeven heads and ten horns, and ſeven crowns on his heads, all which note the ſubtilty, cruelty, ſtrength, and dominion of the Dragon, being the Prince of the power of the air, 6. From a double cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:169844:6"/>the firſt in Execution, the words of my text, <hi>And his tayl drew, &amp;c.</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond in Intention, he had purpoſes of fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther miſchief, the Dragon ſtood before the woman which was ready to be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Here we have news from the Camp, how this weak combatant the Woman comes off at the firſt onſet, with loſſe, ſhe hath a ſeeming rout, we have here,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The party prevailing, expreſſed in [his] ſhape before mentioned with ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven heads and ten horns.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Againſt whom he prevails, the Stars.</p>
            <p n="3">3. How, with his Tayl.</p>
            <p n="4">4. In what he prevails, to draw them from heaven, and caſt them to the earth. The words thus divided, afford this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation.</p>
            <p>Obſ. <hi>The Dragons tayl cauſeth the downfall of many heavenly lights,</hi> Or thus, <hi>A multitude of the Stars of heaven are by the Dragons tayl drawn to the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall clear the Propoſition, by an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering the following Quaeries.</p>
            <div type="question_answered">
               <head>Q. <hi>What we are to underſtand by the Stars of heaven.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Firſt neg: not the laps'd Angels, as
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:169844:6"/>ſome fondly imagine: of whom <hi>Jude</hi> ſpeakes, that they kept not their eſtate, that glorious condition in which they were firſt made, but did of themſelves re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volt from God and the truth. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which move me againſt this opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, are theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe this book is not a Hiſtory <hi>rerum gerundaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> of things don, it relates not paſſages which were then accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſht, but it is a draught and repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of things to be acted, and hereafter to be performed, as <hi>John</hi> himſelf tels us <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.1. the Viſions contained in this book were given him by God, to ſhew unto his ſervants things which muſt ſhortly come to paſſe, now the Angels fell ſome thouſands of years before <hi>John</hi> writ.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Theſe Stars here ſpoken of fell upon the Dragons encounter with the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, they were the ſpoyl he took from her: but the wicked ſpirits apoſtatized from the begining, before ever God had a Church or people in being, the time his decree ſhould bring forth was not yet come.</p>
               <p>Secondly, not the promiſcuous number of thoſe who conſent and joyn toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:169844:7"/>in Apoſtolical doctrine, ſetting it up as a guide and rule of faith and manners; or the company of thoſe who make an outward profeſſion <hi>(i.e.)</hi> viſible Saints, be they Paſtors or People, not having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference at all to any orders conſtituted and appointed by Chriſt in the Church, for though the Godly, if we may ſpeak at large, thoſe that are really or ſeeming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo, taking a view of them in the lump, are Stars of Heaven, every one in their ſeveral orbs and ſtations ſhining in the rayes of Goſpell glory, yet theſe are not the Stars here ſpoken of, but ſome who in gifts and place were more eminent and advanced.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aff.</hi> By Stars therfore in this Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical naration, I conceive the Spirit chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intends, (yet not excluding others,) thoſe who exerciſe miniſterial office, the Paſtors and Teachers of the Church of Chriſt. I take this to be the ſenſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe the Stars in this verſe are the ſame with them in the firſt, which the Woman is crowned with, notwitſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding there is a definite number expreſt twelve; in this we have the conſent of the beſt Expoſitors, that by them are meant the doctrine by the Apoſtles themſelves
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:169844:7"/>publiſhed, which they had from Chriſts own mouth, yet not to be lookt upon with a perſonall reſtriction or limitation to them, for then the Church ever ſince they were bydeath ſilenced, hath loſt her ornament; wherefore it muſt neceſſarily be verified in all thoſe who were their undoubted ſucceſſors, preaching the ſame Chriſt with them, and adminiſtring the ſame Sacraments; in this number of univerſality and perfection, all that pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hold forth the rich grace of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel are included and comprehended.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Becauſe in moſt, if not all, places of this myſterious book, miniſters are called Stars, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.20. The myſtery of the ſeven Stars which thou ſaweſt in my right hand, the ſeven Stars are the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels of the ſeven Churches, <hi>[are,]</hi> doe ſignifie, as the bread is Chriſts body in the Sacrament.</p>
               <p>By Angels in this Epiſtle, we are not to underſtand incorporeall ſubſtances with <hi>Origen,</hi> but Miniſters, and the reaſon is obvious, becauſe God in his ordinary diſpenſation doth not teach the Church by Angels, but by men; the Scripture elſewhere gives Miniſters this honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble appellation, <hi>Hag.</hi> 1.13. and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lachy</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:169844:8"/>ſpeaking of the Prieſts, Chap. 2.7. For he is the Angel of the Lord of hoſts. They are called Angels, Firſt, <hi>Propter vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; miſſionem,</hi> They are miniſtring ſpirits ſent forth, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.14. They act by divine Commiſſion and Authority, ſo all Goſpel Miniſters can ſhew the broad ſeal of heaven. They are employed by the great God to carry on his deſigne of gathering the Elect; I look not upon him as a lawfull Paſtor that hath not a lawfull call, or is not ſent. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.15. of ſuch God complains, as who runne without any miſsion, <hi>Jer.</hi> 14.13. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <hi>Propter munus &amp; officium quo funguntur,</hi> as the Angels are meſſengers to publiſh the mind of God, ſo are alſo Miniſters, as the Apoſtle ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1. To them are committed choice trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure for the enriching of ſouls. Thirdly, <hi>Propter eximiam ſcientiam quâ excellu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</hi> They whoſe lips are to preſerve know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge muſt have more then an ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry competency.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question_answered">
               <head>2. Q <hi>Wherein doth the reſemblance hold, between Stars and Miniſters?</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1 Stars are the cleareſt and brighteſt part of Heaven: ſuch are Paſtors in the firmament of the Church, they ſhould
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:169844:8"/>out-ſhine others in their knowledge of divine myſteries, and have a clearer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight in the hidden things of the Goſpell; they ſhould have a double portion of the Spirit, as was upon <hi>Elijah:</hi> and as they are to be more eminent in ſpirituall endowments and inward qualifications, ſo alſo in a cloſe walking with God, and a Goſpel converſation, they are to benefit others, both by ſoundnes of doctrine, and integrity of life; it is their duty to teach, both by precept, and example.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Stars ſhine not in their own, but a mutatitious light, all their Iuſtre and reſplendency is borrowed from the Sun: ſo what ever gifts of wiſdome and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning, of utterance and opening the mind of Chriſt, are in diſpenſors of the word, it flowes from Ieſus Chriſt, all the beauty, glory, and ſhining of Chriſts Embaſſadors is from him. In the 5 <hi>Mat.</hi> ver. 14. we read, that the Diſciples are the lights of the world, but it is to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by way of participation, not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginally, for Chriſt is called the true light, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.8.9. he only properly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves the name of light, being ſo by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, not by dimanation from another, as the creatures have it; Chriſt is that eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:169844:9"/>uncreated ray, which darts upon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one that is born, both naturall and heavenly light; he is the Sun of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, the great fountain of light, who ſends forth and diſplays his beames for the illumination of all the elect; it is not the ſtudying of Arts &amp; Sciences, it is not skill in tongues and originall languages of Scripture, which can bring us to the knowledge of God; if Chriſt and his Spirit be abſtracted and ſeparated, our apprehenſions will be but hiſtoricall, and notionall ſuch as the Devill may have; when they are ſanctified, and Ieſus Chriſt hath ſhined in, they prove good helps and furtherances; therefore Miniſters muſt look to Chriſt, from whoſe fulneſs all is imparted and communicated, not their own parts and induſtry, without Chriſt and the Spirit they can doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſee 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5, 6. what Goſpell preachers declare is nothing elſe but that which Chriſt brought from the boſome of the Father, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.3.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Stars are wonderfully communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive they affect theſe inferior bodies with influence, motion, and light, they keep not their light to themſelves, but carry and tranſmit it to the world: ſo
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:169844:9"/>Miniſters convey ſpirituall light to men on Earth, living in the dark night of ignorance, error and ſuperſtition; how ſhould they pitty poor ſoules, who ſit in the very ſhadow of death, whoſe eyes are ſo faſt cloſe, that they never ſaw Sun, Moon, or Stars, who never had any light riſen upon them, as is upon us in the Preaching of the word? We are bleſſed that hear the joyfull ſound, the Goſpell trumpet blowing, proclaming liberty to the Captives, &amp;c. But it is ſad to think, the lights of divers places in this Nation are very darkneſs, many thouſands of People are under a dark miniſtery, who are communicative of nothing but their corrupt opinions, and miſunderſtandings of the grace of God to ſinners, of a looſe Goſpell unbecoming life. Bleſſed be God, the Churches hereabouts are better provided, having Miniſters like fixed ſtars, who by the ſweet diſtillation of their lips teach, by the orderly &amp; regular motion of their lives confirm, and by both enlighten many, with ſuch orient heavenly pearls, the Churches, in ſome places, like a bright sky in a clear e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening, ſparkle, and are beſpangled.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question_answered">
               <head>3. Q. <hi>What Pastors are theſe here ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:169844:10"/>by the Stars of Heaven, who are pluckt from their orbs and stations, and drawn to the Earth?</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Neg.</hi> Not fixed Stars. The Dragon cannot move any one faithfull Miniſter of Ieſus Chriſt, he may as ſoon bring Heaven and Earth together, and turn all things into a confuſion, as pluck them from Chriſt in whom they are imbody<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; the reaſon is, becauſe Chriſt holds all thoſe who aime at the glory and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of himſelf, in the nothingneſs of themſelves, in his right hand, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.1. Chriſt holds them, Firſt, <hi>ratione opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis &amp; efficaciae,</hi> in regard of efficacy and operation, it is he that works effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually by the outward adminiſtration of ordinances upon the hearts of men, which are naturally ſhut &amp; baracadoed againſt God and Chriſt, <hi>Act.</hi> 16.14. &amp; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.5. Secondly, <hi>ratione protectionis &amp; custodiae,</hi> in regard of keeping and defence. The right hand in Scripture ſignifies the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and power of God, this ſtreched-out arm is engaged in mantaining the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of his Church; he is indeed a power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full keeper, and a faithfull upholder of all the Saintes, yet ſomtimes he doth make his glory more evidently appear
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:169844:10"/>and ſhine forth in protecting the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. This may bear up the ſpirits of them that are induſtrious in their callings, let them meet with never ſo many diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements and reproaches; what though you are ſcorned by the head-long multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude? what though diſcountenanced by rulers, men in place and Authority? what though the great ones of the world frown upon you? yet let not your hearts fail, only be of a good courage, you are in the right hand of Ieſus Chriſt, and what honour is this to poor Creatures, that he ſhould have ſuch a care of them and love to them? Princes either cannot, or will not vindicate thoſe they imploy, from injuries and affronts, but the Lord Chriſt keeps his ſafe, and is a revenger of the wrongs of thoſe he intruſts, he rebukes even Kings for their ſakes, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Touch not mine anoynted, nor do my Prophets no harm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Aff.</hi> Thoſe Stars which conſiſt of earthly matter, called up by the heat of the Sun, and enlightned by the ſame, (which are more properly called Mete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors, than Stars,) they may, and doe fall: ſo thoſe Paſtors and Teachers, which are earthly and ſenſuall, flouriſht or glided
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:169844:11"/>over only with the light of an outward profeſſion, being exhaled or drawn up by common illuminations, taſts of the good word of God, and powers of the world to come, may be caſt down, and drawn from all that luſtre and glory, with which they did ſhine in the Churches of Chriſt. Now we are not to underſtand theſe Stars any otherwiſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in appearance &amp; opinions of men, which may be diſcerned by their ſhooting from Earth to Heaven, and going out in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity and darkneſs when that matter which ſhould feed them is ſpent, or when ſhaken with the boiſterous winds of temptations and perſecutions, as the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mets doe, which by no means can be ſaid of the heavenly bodies, therefore to be drawn from Heaven to Earth is not to be underſtood literally, but myſtically; it is to fall from a heavenly hope and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, from an imaginary enjoyment of, and living in God, to carnall and earthly practices, to hugging and taſting wordly pleaſures, it is of inhabitants of Heaven to become inhabitants of the Earth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.6.8. we find the diſtinction of theſe 2 ſorts of men; ſuch are all thoſe Paſtors who forſake God &amp; the Goſpel, &amp; buſie
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:169844:11"/>themſelves only about ſecular imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question_answered">
               <head>4. Q. <hi>How may Miniſters be ſaid to fall?</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> They, with all viſible Saints may fall, Firſt in their own judgments, when the fire of heavenly truth, which did ſeemingly ſhine &amp; burn in them, is quite extinquiſhed, and covered over with the Aſhes and Embers of Errors, Lyes Mens Fancies, Licentious Doctrins, which they hold forth as enjoyned by God, father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their fond and groſs conceits upon him; ſuch men are never conſtant and ſetled, but like wandring ſtars, as <hi>Jude</hi> ſpeaks, ver. 13. moving from one opinion to another; like blaſing exhalations, however they may carry it out glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly for a time, yet they ſoon vaniſh &amp; faulter in their motions, whereby the People come to have falſe directions: ſuch men are, in their doctrine, as unſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as reeds, becauſe they follow the guidance of carnall and degenerated reaſon, which hurrieth them into deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive paths, and are not led by the Spirit into the wayes of truth. Secondly, in their affections and practices, when the ſeeming raviſhings in the Spirit, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:169844:12"/>Soule-extaſies are metamorphoſed, and turned into a worldly greedineſs, when leaving the deſires of Gods coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, they gape only after ſuch digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, advancements and preferments, as the creatures ſtore-houſe will afford; when the getting of riches, and applauſe to themſelves, is preferr'd before gaining of Souls to Ieſus Chriſt; inſtead of having their converſation in Heaven, by medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations and earneſt longings, and brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things of heart, they altogether mind Earthly things, they ſet the Moon in the wrong place, above their heads, when it ſhould be under their feet, ſo, as I may ſpeak, glorying in their ſhame; ſuch men are far from <hi>Moſes</hi> temper and diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, elevated and lifted up above the quinteſſence of Creature-glories, he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervalued and ſlighted the beſt of the world, in compariſon of Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.24. by faith he refuſed to be called the Son of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Daughter; he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dopted a Kings Son, he lived in all the delights &amp; pomps of the Court, exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from all trouble, he might have ſome hope in time to ſway the Scepter, &amp; ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed <hi>Pharaoh</hi> in the throne; yet deſpiſing all this dignity, he went to viſit his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:169844:12"/>&amp; choſe rather to ſuffer affliction with the people of God; he ſet more by the reproach of Chriſt, than the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of <hi>Egypt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="question_answered">
               <head>5. Q. <hi>How doth the Dragon obtain ſuch a victory over theſe glorious lights, which once ſparkled in the eradiations of ſound doctrine and holy converſation?</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> By his tayl; that was the means he uſed to give the defeat by, which we are to underſtand,</p>
               <p n="1">1. By his ſtrength and tyrannical op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition. Writers ſay, that the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons main power lyeth in his tayl: we may credit it becauſe the Scripture ſaith as much, <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.19. Their power is in their tayls, for they were like unto Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents, a Dragon is a grown Serpent. Thus by perſecution, ſlaughters, and all the cruelties which wicked men could act or invent, as who are the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons Agents, and carry on his deſignes, many Paſtors and Teachers wanting that boldneſſe and Courage which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes the Souldiers of Chriſt, have fell from their brightneſſe of doctrine, and exemplary walking, to looſe tenets, and corrupt lives; for fear of fire and ſword, they have faſhioned their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:169844:13"/>according to their luſts in their ignorance, according to the Prince of the power of the Ayr.</p>
               <p>Secondly, By daubing inſinuations. Some creatures fawn with their tayls, ſo doth the Dragon; Yet intends never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe miſchief. Thus he comes with the promiſes of outward peace and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſſe, with the enticing baits of pomp and greatneſſe, and ſo in all ages he hath met with, and prevailed upon the ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and covetous humors of divers, who, like <hi>Judas,</hi> to fill the Bagge, have turned againſt their Maſter, or <hi>Eſau,</hi> to ſatisfie their hungry appetites, have choſen the Pottage before the bleſſing.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, By venome and poyſon. The Dragons tayl is full of infection, and with it he deſtroyes and kills the ſouls of multitudes, I mean by falſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, and intoxicating opinions; to broach and vent theſe, he daily ſtirs up perſons whom he furniſheth with the ſubtil guiles and ſophiſtry of hell; by this means in all ages he hath corrupted and tainted divers, who have fallen from ſound Principles, turned their backs, and ſtopt their ears to the charmings of heavenly truth, and whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:169844:13"/>given themſelves up to wicked tenets, contrary to Scripture: He is now gone out as a lying ſpirit in the mouthes of ſome, and hath prevailed; that which Chriſt predicted before his death, that many falſe Chriſts, and falſe Prophets ſhould ariſe and deceive many, we ſee fulfilld in our days; We have many who take upon them a form of Godlineſſe, and in their words and deportment are transformed into Angels of light, whereby they gain and win much upon men, who are led by theſe flouriſhings and varniſhings to follow their pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous wayes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question_answered">
               <head>6. Q. <hi>What was there in the Stars, which haſtned their fall, or further'd the Dragon in caſting them down?</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> It's a truth, that Mans own corruption is his advantage: was it not for that enemy which every one harbors within himſelf, the enemies without him could have but little encouragement to make an Attempt; the beſt of us have Traytors in our boſom, which if God give us not grace to watch over, they will betray us into the hands of our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries; ſuch had theſe Stars, which did them more miſchief than the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon:
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:169844:14"/>Three things eſpecially did bring them down from the top and pinacle of their glory.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Lingring deſires after Creature-vanities, they choak and ſtifle the moſt refined if common gifts of the Spirit; however men may ſeem to burn with zeal for Gods glory, and to be ſet on fire with ardent deſires of fellowſhip with him, yet if they halt between two opinions, having their hearts diſtracted and divided, they will never be able to hold out, when profits and preferments are offered; the World is a ſubtil Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, moſt pleaſing to the diſpoſitions of all, and by reaſon of her vicinity and neighbourhood eaſily and unawares ſteals upon us, and hinders us from the ſeeking and preſſing after better and more enduring Comfort, and content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; how many of thoſe that call themſelves Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt, who like Stars of the firſt magnitude had high places in the Churches, and affections of Gods People, preferring the ſweetneſſe of outward pomp and greatneſſe, before the true honour of being Chriſts Embaſſadors, have with the Serpent crept upon their bellies,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:169844:14"/>and eaten duſt, given themſelves whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to heap up wealth, applauſe among men, and not to exhortation, inſtruction, exemplary walking? Chriſt ſaw cauſe to warn his Diſciples, and in them all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians of the cares of this life, Take heed leſt your hearts be overcharged, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> God and the World cannot dwell to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, they are as contrary as light and darkneſſe, which expell one another from the ſame ſubject. God will have have all the room in our ſouls to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, he muſt be loved with all the heart, and all the ſtrength: Earthly things muſt have none o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our affections; for where they are entertained, they ſhut out God and Chriſt. <hi>Intus exiſtens <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibet alienum,</hi> is true in nature, When a Veſſell is fild with one ſolid body, it cannot receive another; ſo alſo here. Well doth <hi>John</hi> caution beleevers, Love not the world, for if any love the world, the love of the Father is not in him. And <hi>David</hi> a Prophet prayes, Encline mine heart to thy teſtimonies, and not to covetouſneſſe. The Dragon did not leave Chriſt himſelf unaſſailed, when he ſhewed him all the Excellencies of ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene things, he knew it a moſt prevailing
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:169844:15"/>argument, and when this would not do, he fleeeth away, as deſpairing of Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. The want of ſobriety in purſute and uſe of outward bleſſings, ſtains and ſpots the glory of thoſe who take upon them the Office of Stars, to ſhine in the darkneſſe of the world. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> very well compares them to weights, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.1. Earthly things keep men down from aſpiring Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and God-ward, from heaving their ſouls upward, and pluck from heaven when the feet of their ſouls carrie them thither. Men may get as it were into heaven by contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and longings, and obtain a place a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Stars in the view of others, yet, if they doe not ſit looſe from the World, and are not gathered up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the Moon, they will ſoon deſcend, like a heavy body, which ſo ſoon as the violence forcing it ceaſeth, afterwards of its own accord tends to the Center. Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, above all, ſhould have their hearts weaned, as <hi>Davids</hi> was, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 13.1, 3. <hi>Hannah</hi> had devoted <hi>Samuel</hi> to God, to ſpend all his days in and about the Tabernacle in <hi>Shilo,</hi> however ſhe brings him not thither as ſoon as he was
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:169844:15"/>born, but firſt Weans him, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.22.24. he could not have abode in the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, had he not been Weaned; though a man be drawn up to Heaven, and numbred among the Coeleſtial bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, yet if he be not Weaned from the Earth, he will not long continue there, he will be hankering after the worlds breaſts, he will ſpeedily come down to ſuck that Milk.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Not placing their chief hapineſs in things above; they did not make heavenly things their treaſures, they hoarded not up there, how can they be in Heaven and ſtay there, when their affections are not there? and the only way to get their hearts into Heaven, is to get their treaſures into Heaven. So ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.20, 21. The heart and the treaſure are indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, not to be ſeparated; where the Carcaſſe is, there will the Eagles be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together: Chriſts Eagles mount aloft, and ſit with him in heavenly pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Chriſt among other beauties of the Church takes notice of this, as a ſpeciall one, <hi>Cant.</hi> 7.4. her Noſe is like the Tower of <hi>Lebanon,</hi> one would have lookt upon this, as a deformity and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendation,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:169844:16"/>but by it, is ſet forth, that ſpirituall ſagacity and quicknes of ſmell, whereby the Saints reſent and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour things above, being carried after Chriſt, the true Carcaſs, with unſpeakable pleaſure and delight: but ſome have their Senſes and Noſes in the earth, with the Swine, as themſelves are of the earth; po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions, inheritances, are the things alone ſweet to them, therefore they cannot be long abſent. Would we therfore like true Stars be immoveable &amp; unſhaken, let us make Chriſt our treaſure, let our cry be, None but Chriſt, none but Chriſt, let him be precious to us as to all beleevers, the welbeloved of our Souls, the pearl of great price, let all things elſe be counted as loſe and dung in compariſon of him. The Sun extracts vapours, ſo doth the Son of righteouſnes the affections of his people. When Chriſt is lifted up in the deſires and eſteem of men, he drawes to and keeps them with him. Where the loadſtone is, that way it draws Iron, if beneath it brings it down, if above it brings it up: many deſcend, becauſe their loadſtone is in the Earth, but thoſe that pitch their loadſtone in heaven, make Chriſt their loadſtone, need not fear
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:169844:16"/>their continuance in Heaven.</p>
               <p n="3">3dly, The want of an intrinſicall principle of grace. I grant they had an Extrinſicall flouriſh, but they were far from inward diſpoſitions, elſe the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons tail had never prevailed. Hence is it that they could not make any long ſtay above. Stars which fall &amp; go out are taken up by an outward agent as the Sun: ſo thoſe Paſtors w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> appear to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe and live in Heaven, and afterwards are precipitated to the earth, were never drawn up by their own proper inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which did proceed from ſomething within themſelves, but by the outward workings of the Spirit. Heavy things we know go downward, becauſe naturall propenſity inclines them to deſcend; ſo light things go aloft, becauſe they have an in nat principle carrying the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that way: ſo thoſe teachers which continue in their orbs, &amp; the Dragons tail cannot hurt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, have ſuch a frame of ſpirit, that is ſtill lifting their hearts on high, ſuch are in a ſure and ſafe condition, the gates of hell cannot prevail againſt them. I deny not, but the beſt may have ſome diverſions and clogs upon them, which may hinder and take them off for a time, from God and Chriſt, and heavenly things; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:169844:17"/>they will never be at reſt, untill they are ſet that way again. The needle of the Compaſs if once touched with the Loadſtone, may by ſome violent motion be ſhaken from its reſt, yet if it be let alone, it will not ceaſe till it comes to the North point: ſo when a mans ſpirit is touched with Chriſt, he may notwithſtanding be acquainted with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions and worldy incumbrances, yet his heart will never give over working and moving till it is again center'd in him. There is a fire comming down from God of an active aſpiring nature, that falls upon all faithfull Paſtors of Chriſt, and burns and conſumes all Earthlineſſe and carnality, and cauſes them to aſcend to God, it makes hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly thoughts goe up like pillars of ſmoak; Fire doth not more naturally ariſe, than grace in a ſanctified heart cauſes that ſoul to make aſcenſions into heaven.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="application">
               <p>
                  <hi>Uſe.</hi> Let me tell you, who are glitte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Lamps of heaven, moving in the ſphere of Chriſts right hand, that you are expoſed to the rage of the Dragon, you are not freed from his tayl, he will endeavor the caſting of you down from your ſhining in the Church of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:169844:17"/>Chriſt, he covets the Crown of Stars on the Womans head, which makes her ſo glorious to beholders, he knows ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well that God hath appointed you to rule the night, that by you he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſes and ſcatters the light of heavenly truth to the dark erronious World, he underſtands how deſtructive and preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall your influences are to his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes and purpoſes, who holds men and women in ſubjection to himſelf by ignorance, blindneſſe and ſuperſtition; he is not ignorant wherefore God ſet up your function, to batter and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en his Kingdom, and to advance the Scepter of his Sonne: We find therefore in all Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtories he hath moſt ſet himſelf againſt, and oppoſed the faithfull Miniſters of Ieſus Chriſt, and by Clouds and tempeſts endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the eclipſing of their glorie, and depriving the Churches of the Stars lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre: ſo he dealt with thoſe by whom the Goſpel was firſt noyſed and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded abroad, <hi>Rev.</hi> 8.7. By Angels there I doe not underſtand thoſe, who are ſo <hi>ex naturâ,</hi> by nature, the immateriall beings, but <hi>ex officio,</hi> by office, an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical ſpirit in men concionally pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clayming the glad tydings of peace, by
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:169844:18"/>the trumpets, I conceive there is an il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion to thoſe ſpoken of <hi>Numb.</hi> 10.1, 2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which God appointed the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to uſe for gathering of Aſſemblies, and which were blown at the year of <hi>Iubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lee,</hi> a type of a more joyful ſound, which <hi>David</hi> calls them happy who hear, even that ſung by the heavenly quire, On Earth peace, good will towards men, The meaning is, when the Apoſtles and Primitive Preachers firſt began to divulge the grace of God, the Dragon by ſlaughters, and maſſacres, did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to hinder the Eccho of it to the world, and by theſe ſtorms the third part of the trees, a great many excellent lights, faithful meſſengers of Chriſt, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared here to Trees, for their fruitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ſhadow, were conſumed, and others profeſſing Chriſt, by the heat of thoſe flames were ſcorcht and burnt to aſhes, called graſſe for their imbecillity, and ſubjection to caſualities, and green, <hi>propter fidei &amp; charitatis vigorem,</hi> this is an alluſion to the 7th <hi>Egyptian</hi> Plague, <hi>Exod.</hi> 9.24. And I think it to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood rather of the calamities that fell upon the godly, than the wicked, becauſe they are compared to Trees in Scripture, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.3. When the ſecond Angel blew,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:169844:18"/>[A great Mountain] Empires, Kings, and Tyrants, who ſwell, and are big with pride and power, are ſo called, that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulation we read of <hi>Zach.</hi> 4.7. Who art thou great Mountain? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is true in the Letter of the <hi>Perſian</hi> Monarchy; by it therefore is meant ſome mighty Kingdom, whether <hi>Roman,</hi> or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I ſhall not determine [burning with fire] that is, Anger and rage, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all thoſe that had not the mark of the Beaſt; the fumes and vapors iſſuing out of it, were threatnings and revenge [caſt into the Sea] the gatherng toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the waters God called Sea: ſuch, ſuch are men being unſtable and violent, therefore compared to the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in of a Floud; the Sea here is the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſality and multitude of Nations, People and Languages: This Mountain with fury and madneſſe ruſheth into the world, what then? the third part of the Sea became blood. The horſe on which Chriſt rides, his Church, which bears his name, changeth colour from white to red, being all beſmeared with the blood of Martyrs, divers were cruſhed with the weight of this Mountain, the third part of creatures died, that is thoſe did profeſſe Chriſt, and the third part of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:169844:19"/>ſhips were deſtroyed, the Churches whoſe Paſtors are their Pilots. Now if ever it concerns you, look to your ſelves, for the Dragon is come down in great wrath, though not in hail &amp; blood min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with fire, yet we may perceive the ſad effects of his tayl in the putting out of ſome, owned for great lights. The third Angel is now ſounding, <hi>Rev.</hi> 8.10. And there fell a great Star from heaven. I ſhall not ſo far impair the large extent of this Propheſie, to think <hi>Pelagius</hi> the Star here ſpoken of, or any other Haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiarch, as many do, who was a ſtout champion of Free will, and an oppoſer of Original ſin; he fell from heaven by his defection, from the Church of Chriſt on earth, great in regard of learning, not without a ſhew of religion, by which he deceived many; thus he burned like a lamp the name is called <hi>Wormwood,</hi> v. 11. he taught that which was contrary to the ſweetneſſe of the grace of Chriſt, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Man by pure naturals might convert and ſave himſelf, by this, and ſuch like peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and bitter doctrines, <hi>Magnam par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem Epiſcoporum amaricavit &amp; perdidit,</hi> however this is a truth, though not with reſpect to the perſon of any, yet to the ſucceſſion, and things themſelves, our age
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:169844:19"/>bears ſufficient witneſſe, not only a Star, but Stars are fallen from heaven, called <hi>Wormwood,</hi> that is, ſome Paſtors are fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len from purity of doctrine, which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly they did maintain, and have taken up the bitter morſels of humane inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, errors, ambition, covetouſneſſe, and this is caſt into the rivers and fountains of water, that is, the ſame infection hath tainted &amp; imbitter'd others, even a third part of thoſe who pretend to be Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt, by whom, as by fountains, the wholſom and ſweet ſtreams of ſound and incorrupted doctrine ſhould have flowed, for the refreſhing of the People of God. However theſe flouds of errors and falſe doctrines ruſh in and threaten an inundation and overwhelming, yet the faithful Miniſters of the Goſpel need not fear, for it ſhall not reach them: let the waters roar and make a noiſe, they are kept ſafe, as <hi>Noah</hi> in the Ark, from periſhing, let times and places be never ſo bad in which they live theſe conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations may comfort and ſupport them.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Com.con.</hi> God will not ſuffer the Dragon to break aſunder his order, whereby he hath appointed to teach and call men, the Miniſtry is Gods Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, of his own eſtabliſhing, and being
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:169844:20"/>of God it will ſtand, a number will be left, though the gates of Hell oppoſe, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to ſerve his providence in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of ſouls. Doe but meditate a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle on the ſtability of Gods decrees, the Councell of the Lord ſhall ſtand. Wee vary in our opinions and apprehenſions, not the ſame yeſterday as to day, but Chriſt is the ſame, yeſterday, and to day, and the ſame for ever; Nothing can ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject him to a mutation; no power or policy can prevent his purpoſes, he hath committed the word of reconciliation to men: Therefore there muſt be a ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of men, to hold forth this word in ſeverall ages to the worlds end. Its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, the Lord, with whom is wiſdom and ſtrength can without and againſt means, immediately by himſelf ſave his people, but for his own greater glory he will ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doe it by weak inſtruments, carried on, and aſſiſted with his own out-ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched arm, which all the Dragons can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not prevail againſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Com.con.</hi> The bleſſing of the Church belongs to Ieſus Chriſt, who hath under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken to furniſh it with Paſtors, till his appearing in glory, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.11. Chriſt after his aſcenſion and compleat inaugu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, as the Fathers Plenipotentiary,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:169844:20"/>or as it is the manner of Kings at their Coronations, gave gifts to men, ſome for Apoſtles, &amp; ſome Teachers, for the edify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his own body: the manifeſtation of the Spirit, is not beſtowed for ſelf-ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, or to get eſteem with men, but for the benefit &amp; profit of Chriſts mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. The office of the high Prieſt under the Law, did notably repreſent and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pifie the Office of Chriſt in the Goſpel, he had the care of the lights of the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary, and was to keep them from go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out, therefore he did ſee to the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying of them with oyl; the Dragon may ſtrive to blow out all the lights God hath ſet up in the Church, but Chriſt who wakes in the middeſt of the ſeven golden Candleſticks, hath an eye always over them, &amp; takes care that they never want the unction of the Spirit.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Com.con.</hi> Chriſt is always preſent with the Prophets of the New Teſtament; when he ſent out his Diſciples and char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged them to teach all Nations, it is like their carnal hearts, which did dote much upon Chriſts fleſhly preſence, ſcrupled the ſucceſs of their preaching; what we poor Fiſhermen ſet upon the world, and preach a Chriſt, every where ſpoken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, and hated? Its expedient indeed,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:169844:21"/>ſaith Chriſt, that I goe away, and take this body from the Earth, yet you ſhall be no loſers, I will be with you by my Spirit and gracious aſſiſtance to the end of the World. Sometime indeed Chriſt may ſeem to abſent himſelf, and retire from his conflicting ſervants, he may pour out upon them hayl, and fire ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with hail, and ſmite them; he may caſt down fiery mountains and bruiſe them, yet Chriſt is in the fire, and in the hayl, although his people cannot ſee him; however the Dragon may ſo far prevail, as to overcome ſome in reſpect of their Perſon, yet he cannot in reſpect of their Faith; by this they overcome the world and hell.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Com.con.</hi> The remuneration or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward which through the merits of Chriſt ſhall be given thoſe, whom God honors with gaining of People to Chriſt, and makes inſtrumental in opening their eys, he will crown with an exceeding weight of glory, ſuch, as they are now hoaſts of heaven or Saints of high-places, ſo here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after they ſhall ſhine like the Sun in the Firmament, or Stars for evermore.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:169844:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
